Finding Aid for the Shinkichirō Shima papers, 1894-1965
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Shinkichirō Shima papers,
1894-1965
2010
Shima, Shinkichirō (島辰吉朗)
3 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
University of California, Los Angeles. Library. Department of Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Shinkichirō Shima was born in 1877 in Fukuoka Prefecture, Japan, and arrived at San Francisco in 1894. He was a devoted Christian and poet, and worked as a cactus nurseryman in Southern California. During World War II, he was incarcerated in the Manzanar Relocation Center. The collection consists of a diary, correspondence, religious poems and various religious writings.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Biography
Shinkichirō Shima was born in 1877 in Fukuoka Prefecture, Japan, and arrived at San Francisco in 1894 on board the Empress of China. He was baptized at a Methodist church in 1898 and became a devoted Christian. During World War II, he was incarcerated in the Santa Ana Assembly Center and transferred to the Manzanar Relocation Center on July 31, 1942. In the Manzanar Relocation Center, he joined the Guayule project, propagating rubber plans. He was also a poet and worked as a cactus nurseryman in Southern California, exporting cacti to Japan.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of a diary, correspondence, and various writings related to the life of Shinkichirō Shima. The diary, in Japanese, begins when he left Yokohama for the United States on board the Empress of China (October 9, 1894) with subsequent entries made on memorable occasions. It includes descriptions of voyages when Shima traveled between the U.S. and Japan from 1898 to 1918, and documents the matters of his cactus export business to Japan. It also covers the time period when Shima was incarcerated in the Santa Fe Assembly Center and the Manzanar Relocation Center (1942-1946), depicting life in the camps in a Japanese poetic form.
Three notebooks contain his drafts of letters, in English and Japanese, some of which were written in the Manzanar Relocation Center while he was incarcerated. These include descriptions of camp life conditions as well as his participation in the Guayule project to propagate rubber plants at the Manzanar Relocation Center, and his family situations in Japan. The drafts also include English letters asking his friends to manage his bank accounts and Japanese letters discussing business plans for trading between US and Japan.
Other writings include manuscripts for religious poems, 霊帳 Reichō, Daily blessing, hymns compiled in a Japanese poetic form in the Manzanar Relocation Center, excerpts from the Bible and verses, and other religious writings.
Organization and Arrangement
Materials are arranged as follows:
Personal papers (Box 136)
Hymns in a Japanese poetic form (Box 136)
霊帳 Reichō (Box 136)
Manuscripts for "Daily blessing" (Box 137)
Religious poems and various religious writings (Boxes 137-138)
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Shima, Shinkichirō, 1877- --Archives.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles).; Authors, Japanese--Archival resources.; Japanese Americans--California, Southern--Archival resources.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at the Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
Container List
Shinkichirō Shima papers are found in Boxes 136-138 of the Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010).
- Shima papers, 1894-1965; 1.5 linear ft.
  Shima Shinkichirō (1877- ). Cactus nurseryman, Southern California. A native of Fukuoka Prefecture who arrived in America in 1894. Poet and devout Christian.
  - Biographical data, : undated (Box 136, Folder 1)
    Eight pieces of scratch paper containing brief biographical information on Shima. Memorable occasions from 1877 through 1933 were documented chronologically. In English and Japanese.
  - Diary, : 1894-circa 1950 (Box 136, Folder 2)
    One unbound notebook of diary beginning on Oct. 9, 1894 when Shima left Yokohama, Japan, on board the Empress of China for the United States. Subsequent entries were made only on memorable occasions. In Japanese.
  - Diary, : 1949 December 22-1950 February 7 (Box 136, Folder 3)
    One notebook of diary. Poems are also included. In Japanese.
  - Drafts of letters, : 1942 August 6-circa 1946, May, 1959 (Box 136, Folder 4)
    Three notebooks containing drafts of letters written by Shima: Two notebooks were written in the Manzanar Relocation Center from August 6, 1942 to ca. May 1946; and one notebook contains drafts of letters written in ca. 1959, poems, and some account notes. In English and Japanese.
  - Correspondence, : circa 1954-1965 (Box 136, Folder 5)
    Incoming correspondence from Oral Roberts, Oral Roberts Evangelistic Association, Tulsa, Oklahoma, and others. Materials also include two letters from Japanese Research Institute of Rare Plants and Animals regarding Cactus business. In English and Japanese.
  - Immigration documents, : undated (Box 136, Folder 6)
    Application for a certificate of arrival and preliminary form for a declaration of intention.
  - Naturalization examination, : after 1950 (Box 136, Folder 7)
    One booklet and two pieces of study notes for the naturalization examination. In English.
  - Address book, : 1951-1955, 1960-1963 (Box 136, Folder 8)
    One address book for Christmas cards and gifts. In Japanese.
  - Financial documents, : 1958 November 30, 1959 August 29 (Box 136, Folder 9)
    Two pieces of financial documents. In English.
  - 豊前人同志會創立趣意書 Buzenjin Dōshikai setsuritsu shuisho, : 1934 December (Box 136, Folder 10)
    A leaflet containing objectives for 豊前人同志會 Buzenjin Dōshikai, an association for people from the Buzen region, Japan. In Japanese.
  - 南加福岡県人会·婦人会 Nanka Fukuoka Kenjinkai and Fujinkai, : ca.1957 October-1961 March (Box 136, Folder 11)
    Leaflets regarding 南加福岡県人会 Nanka Fukuoka Kenjinkai [Association for People from Fukuoka Prefecture] and 南加福岡婦人会 Nanka Fukuoka Fujinkai [Women's Association for People from Fukuoka Prefecture]
  - 信用貯金組合人事相談部創立の趣意 Shin'yō Chochiku Kumiai Jinji Sōdanbu sōritsu no shui, : undated (Box 136, Folder 12)
    One piece of scratch paper containing objectives for establishment of an office in a trust bank which assists their church members in making savings. Written by Shima and Takai Ikuo.
  - Religious leaflet, : 1948 (Box 136, Folder 13)
    A leaflet including religious poems circulated by Shima. In Japanese.
  - Hymns, : 1943 January 1, and undated (Box 136, Folder 14)
    Two notebooks of hymns in a Japanese poetic form compiled by Shima; one was compiled in the Manzanar Relocation Camp; and the date of the other notebook is unknown. In Japanese.
  - Manuscripts for 霊帳 Reichō, : undated (Box 136, Folder 15)
    Three notebooks including manuscripts for 霊帳 Reichō, a collection of Shima's poems. In Japanese.
  - 霊帳 Reichō, : 1958 November (Box 136, Folder 16)
    One privately-printed book including a collection of Shima's poems; and an estimate for its publication. In Japanese.
  - Manuscripts for "Daily blessing", : 1962 January 1-1964 December 31 (Box 137, Folder 1)
    Three notebooks and three pieces of paper containing manuscripts for "Daily blessing" written from January 1, 1962 through December 31, 1964. In English and Japanese.
  - Manuscripts for "Daily blessing", : 1965 January 1-December 25 (Box 137, Folder 2)
    Manuscripts for "Daily blessing" written from January 1 through December 25, 1965. In English and Japanese.
  - Manuscripts for "Daily blessing", : probably 1966 January 1-30, March 1-April 28 (Box 137, Folder 3)
    Manuscripts for "Daily blessing" written probably in 1966, January 1-30, and March 1-April 28. In English and Japanese.
  - Religious writings (1 of 2), : undated (Box 137, Folder 4)
    Four notebooks containing collections of various religious writings. In Japanese.
  - Religious writings (2 of 2), : undated (Box 137, Folder 5)
    Five notebooks containing collections of various religious writings. In Japanese.
  - Religious poems (1 of 3), : 1942-circa 1957, and undated (Box 137, Folder 6)
    Twenty seven pieces of scratch paper containing manuscripts of religious poems composed by Shima. In Japanese and English.
  - Religious poems (2 of 3), : undated (Box 137, Folder 7)
    Four notebooks containing manuscripts of religious poems composed by Shima. In Japanese and English.
  - Religious poems (3 of 3), : undated (Box 137, Folder 8)
    Three notebooks containing manuscripts of religious poems composed by Shima. In Japanese and English.
  - Religious poems with reading notes (1 of 2), : 1901-1910 (Box 138, Folder 1)
    One notebook containing reading notes and religious poems composed by Shima.
  - Religious poems with reading notes (2 of 3), : undated (Box 138, Folder 2)
    Religious poems composed by Shima. Includes reading notes on the Japanese translation of "The manhood of the master" written by Harry Emerson Fosdick and "修養の友 Shūyō no tomo" by 吉村末吉 Yoshimura Suekichi. In Japanese.
  - Religious poems with reading notes (3 of 3), : undated (Box 138, Folder 3)
    Religious poems composed by Shima. Includes reading notes for "愛の暦 Ai no koyomi," the Japanese translation of Leo Tolstoy's work, and works of 賀川豊彦 Kagawa Toyohiko. Primarily in Japanese with some in English.
  - Religious poems with religious writings (1 of 3), : undated (Box 138, Folder 4)
    Collections of various manuscripts for religious poems with verses in the Bible and other religious writings. Primarily in Japanese, with texts in English.
  - Religious poems with religious writings (2 of 3), : undated (Box 138, Folder 5)
  - Religious poems with religious writings (3 of 3), : undated (Box 138, Folder 6)
  - Document on loyalty, : undated (Box 138, Folder 7)
    One item documenting "忠 chū" [loyalty] in Japanese.